<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The introduction to the true understanding of the whole arte of expedition in teaching to write Intermixed with rare discourses of other matters, to shew the possibilitie of skill in teaching, and probabilitie of successe in learning, to write in 6. hours. Which tending all to one end, doe serve for two uses. 1. If authors doe excell others in their owne artes, why may not this author excell others in his arte. 2. For removing a vulgare opinion against his native countrey of Scotland, he sheweth that it hath moe excellent prerogatives than any other Kingdome. Whereby it will rather follow, that a Scotishman is so much the more able to prosecute whatsoever hee undertaketh, and therefore so much the more to bee respected, by how so much he is more ingenuous than one of another nation.</title>
            <author>Browne, David, fl. 1622-1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117068</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852283</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852283</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1129:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The introduction to the true understanding of the whole arte of expedition in teaching to write Intermixed with rare discourses of other matters, to shew the possibilitie of skill in teaching, and probabilitie of successe in learning, to write in 6. hours. Which tending all to one end, doe serve for two uses. 1. If authors doe excell others in their owne artes, why may not this author excell others in his arte. 2. For removing a vulgare opinion against his native countrey of Scotland, he sheweth that it hath moe excellent prerogatives than any other Kingdome. Whereby it will rather follow, that a Scotishman is so much the more able to prosecute whatsoever hee undertaketh, and therefore so much the more to bee respected, by how so much he is more ingenuous than one of another nation.</title>
                  <author>Browne, David, fl. 1622-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Harper [in London] and J. Wreittoun [in Edinburgh]],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London and Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: David Brovvn.</note>
                  <note>Places of publication and printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Wreittoun apparently only printed the first 2 leaves--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The introduction to the true understanding of the whole worke.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penmanship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INTRODVCTION to the true underſtanding of the <hi>whole Arte of Expedition in</hi> teaching to write.</p>
            <p>Intermixed with rare diſcourſes of other matters, to ſhew the poſſibilitie of skill in teaching, and probabilitie of ſucceſſe in learning, to write in 6. hours</p>
            <p>Which tending all to one end, doe ſerve for two uſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If Authors doe excell others in their owne Artes, Why may not this Author excell others in his Arte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For removing a vulgare opinion against his native coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of</hi> Scotland. <hi>he ſheweth that it hath moe excellent Prerogatives than any other Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby it will rather follow, that a Scotiſhman is ſo much the more able to proſecute whatſoever <hi>hee undertaketh, and therefore ſo much the more to bee reſpected, by how ſo much he is</hi> more ingenuous than one of another nation.</p>
            <p>Anno Dom. 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS</hi> AND HOPEFVLL PRINCE, <hi>CHARLES Prince of</hi> WALES, <hi>&amp;c. temporall</hi> proſperitie and endleſſe felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay it pleaſe your Highneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In regard that ſome have a ſiniſter opinion of me in my profeſſion, not only becaus of the pretended impoſſibility of the ſucces therof, but far more of that worthie nation, where all your Highneſſe moſt royall Progenitors had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and whereof I alſo have the honour to be a native, and leſt any either of their writings or ſpeaches ſhould come to your Highneſse ſight or hearing, now in your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der yeares, I have laboured heere to preuent them, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending both my Countrie and profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Where as theſe things are propounded heere in the ſuperlative degree, I ſuppoſe it is according to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of worthy men in former times, when their perſons, profeſſions, countries, or cauſes have beene any wayes traduced, they have not only defended the ſame to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of their power, but even ſtretched all and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo-ever their properties priviledges, or liberties to the furtheſt extent, that their adverſaries might bee either convinced or ſilenced.</p>
            <p>Whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God your Highneſſe ſhall have occaſion to uſe that antient nation, yea or any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof (ſuch as my ſelf) in any ſervice, I hope your Highneſſe ſhall find us as faithfull, able and willing now, as our predeceſſors have beene to your Highneſſe royall progenitours informer times.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:3"/>
            <p> Now in token of my goodwill and affection, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſent your Highneſſe with theſe my meane labours, that they may goe abroad under your Highneſſe protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that it would pleaſe God to grant your Highneſſe ſuch gratious education, as you may bee an happie inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his glorie in his owne good time, it ſhall be the fervent ſuite of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe humble ſervant, <hi>DAVID BROVVN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:3"/>
            <head>In D. Davidis Bruni Calligraphiam novam.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ILle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſonet quimentis acumine fretus</l>
               <l>Protulit, in tenebris quae latuere prius</l>
               <l>At ſi quis noſtros artem quae cedat in uſûs</l>
               <l>Invenit, inventum perficit at que ſuum;</l>
               <l>Ille quidem plenis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> buccis</l>
               <l>Perſonet, inventas dum ſibi prodit opes.</l>
               <l>Non has Aſſyrius laudes, aut Helladis ora</l>
               <l>Quos dedit, aut claros terra latina Sophos;</l>
               <l>Non ſibi Niliaci tribuent: Nam poſtuma ſemper</l>
               <l>Aetas excoluit quod rude prima dedit.</l>
               <l>At modo ſcribendi leges dum tradit &amp; artem,</l>
               <l>Haec ſibi qui merito vendicet unus erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. CARFORDIVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <head>Philographo.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VSus ut artifices faciat, ars dirigit: aptas</l>
               <l>Scripturae, hîc normas, quam cupis, artis habes.</l>
               <l>Brunius ecce dedit: ſi primus, reddere primas</l>
               <l>Aequum eſt: artifici convenit artis honos.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>PATRICIVS SANDAEVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <lg>
               <l>THough uſe makes skill, yet art directs,</l>
               <l>Here Maſter <hi>Browne</hi> the rules detects,</l>
               <l>Since he the ſame doth firſt diſcover,</l>
               <l>The praiſe with him remaines for ever.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>JO. DICK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſumme of the Authors Profeſſion of</hi> EXPEDITION, <hi>in teaching to Write.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E teacheth thoſe that can reade, and bee capable and carefull, <hi>to write any hand well in ſixe houres,</hi> which they never wrote before, or to rectifie whatſoever hand they write already; each one in a ſeverall roome, and halfe an houre at a time.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Others alſo hee teacheth in ſo much longer time, as they come ſhort of ſuch abilitie, capacitie, or uſing the meanes: which conſiſts both in earneſt performing their daily halfe hours taske, when they have beſt leyſure betweene the times of teaching, and in carefull ſupplying the defect, loſſe, or neglect of any one time, by ſo much the more care and diligence at another time.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And thoſe that cannot write at all, or not well, or not true Engliſh, neither can reade written hand, write without rule, nor keepe accounts, he teacheth to attaine all theſe better in one Month, an houre onely in a day, and as long by their owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate practiſe, (when their affaires may bee leaſt hindred) then they can by others, after the ordinary manner in three, though they ſhould ſpend all the day, neglect all other buſineſſe, and doe nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>All by true and exact method new Rules, and rare ſecrets of art; authorized by Supreme Authoritie; approved by the State, embraced by the Learned, attained by the Ignorant, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Author &amp; Profeſſor, againſt all oppoſers and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyers, ſtrangers and others.</p>
            <p>For redeeming the time, and renewing the occaſion of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to all, but chiefly thoſe of middle age, who have wanted, loſt, or neglected either, in their youth, and cannot now ſpare long time to learne.</p>
            <p>He practiſeth the moſt part of the day in the Terme time, and moſt of the after noone in the vacation, at the <hi>Cat</hi> and <hi>Fiddle</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and moſt of the forenoone, at his houſe in S. <hi>Iohns</hi> ſtreet, next above the Vnicorne, except when hee is invited to the Country at any time, eſpecially in the long vacation.</p>
            <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re likewiſe <hi>Mary Stewart</hi> and her daughters, doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t young Noble and Gentlewomen in good manners, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, writing, &amp; other qualities, by his aſſiſtance &amp; direction.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:4"/>
            <head>THE INTRODVCTION to the true underſtanding of the whole Booke.</head>
            <head type="sub">Shewing (as in a proſpect) both the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of <hi>Expedition,</hi> in teaching, faire, ſhort, and true writing; and the poſſibilitie of learning to <hi>write any hand in ſixe houres.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it hath pleaſed our gratious God of his great bounty, for his owne glory, and mans felicity, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre man to all his creatures on earth, and to adorne him with many excellent prerogatives, gifts, and faculties, farre above all the reſt, ſuch as wiſedome, knowledge, and learning; ſo likewiſe he hath ordained all good Arts and Sciences, as ſpeciall helps and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanes whereby he may attaine thereunto, and ſo much the better, both enjoy a comfortable life here, and the hope of a happy life hereafter: for as hee ever appointeth the end, ſo he alwaies appointeth the means to come to the end.</p>
            <p>And ſince the knowledge and practiſe of Arts and Sciences, can neither be ſo well nor ſpeedily attained,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:5"/> as by uſing the ordinary meanes, preſcribed by thoſe whom it hath pleaſed God to raiſe up and indue with gifts above the reſt in every age; and that by the help or inſtruction of ſuch as have beene moſt expert for the time; and thoſe who are expert in theſe dayes (now as well as in former times) are ſo rare, that they can ſcarcely be had, but only in ſome eminent Cities: and in no Arte or Science, are they more rare, then in this of writing, although it maintaineth all other Arts and Sciences.</p>
            <p>I therefore, not onely in conſideratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe, and many other motives, but likewiſe being further moved by the earneſt in treaty of ſome vertuous min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded men, who now in their age, doe far more ſenſibly feele the want, neglect, or loſſe of time in their youth, then many others who are little more carefull yet, than they were then; and ſo much the rather, in that I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ſome meaſure of ability in my ſelfe for their nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt remedy or beſt recoverie, (as they are now) have thought it both a part of my duty to him of whom I have it, and very needfull and expedient for the good of all, being the chiefe end wherefore I received it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to offer the ſame as a benefit to all, and that by publiſhing this Booke to the view of the world, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth they, and all others, may make a profitable uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>For it may be, that many hundreths, who are both paſt the date of (going to ſchooles) and much employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about other buſineſſes, will yet ſpare ſome conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time to learne alone, by the helpe of this Booke; whereas (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither through diſtance of place, or other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions) ſeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly one of them can come to me, or will goe to others: which whoſoever readeth or practiſeth, I wiſh it may be done orderly as it ſtandeth, without any omiſſion at all, and as little intermiſſion as poſſibly may be, that the ſcope and ſubſtance of all, being once well conceived in the minde, it may be ſo much both ſpeedier and better practiſed by the hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> If either thou that diligently readeſt, or but lightly vieweſt, or yet any of you that heare or ſee this booke, be ſuch as neither need, nor intend to learne; or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if yee, or any of you be ignorant, and therefore yee apprehending your owne neceſſities, would faine learne, but want either meanes or opportunity; or yet be ſuch as have both great need, and earneſt deſire, but too late for you now to begin: I could wiſh it might pleaſe you not to judge or cenſure this Booke, or bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit offered therein, either as ye are, or ſhall be in any of theſe caſes or conditions.</p>
            <p>But rather, as if ye your ſelves, or any of you had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther written the one, or offered the other, or perchance thrice ſo good as either; and would have me, or others of better judgement and diſcretion, to judge or cenſure thoſe your workes or fruits thereof, and ſo eſteeme of you accordingly.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Or, as if
<list>
                     <item>Ye were to be learners, and did feele to your great griefe now, the want, loſſe, or neglect of learning formerly, and could get no other helpe (under God) to teach you.</item>
                     <item>Ye were in danger to loſe ſome good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, which if you could but write a legible hand, you might eaſily obt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ine.</item>
                     <item>Ye were come to ſuch age, as you would think it a diſparagement to goe to ſchoole.</item>
                     <item>Your affaires would not permit, though you would bee content to goe.</item>
                     <item>You might ſpare ſome little time to learne this way, though no time any other way.</item>
                     <item>Your children, friends, neighbours, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſtood in need of inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cting.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Or, moſt of all, I wiſh ye may judge or cenſure this Booke or benefit, as it may be profitable to the Church or Common wealth, whereof you are members; for in that regard, it doth alſo concern you all, in what eſtate ſoever you are; yea, and the more wiſe or learned you be, I hope you will ſo much the better acknowledge,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:6"/> that that which is a benefit to others (by the ſimpathy of fellow members) is alſo a benefit to you: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye are not onely to approve, but even to maintain alſo according to your power at all times and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whatſoever is for the good of others, although neither any of you, not any of yours at ſome time or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, have any particular need thereof your ſelves.</p>
            <p>But ſince that which is written, may indure, when the dayes of the actor, as well as the time of the action, will expire, who knoweth but that which I intend herein may both continue and doe good to many one, when neither my hand can write, nor my tongue ſpeake to any at all? I will therefore take occaſion (howſoever to doe my part, and not onely now begin whiles I have breath) by the meanes of writing, to write the <hi>ſpeedy and true way, both of teaching and learning to write;</hi> but likewiſe uſe my beſt indeavours to <hi>performe it with all my power, for there is neither wiſedome, worke, nor invention in the grave whither I goe;</hi> and referre both the continuance and event to God, who onely is eternall, and hath the ſucceſſe of all things in his hands.</p>
            <p>Whom I humbly beſeech ſo to guide and direct me, both in doing thereof, and whatſoever thing elſe I take in hand, that not onely I may ſet his Majeſtie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies before my eyes, and keepe my ſelfe in the meane betweene theſe two extremities, even neither to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the name of a ſluggard, by doing nothing (at leaſt worth the name of any thing) nor yet to be wiſe in my owne conceit, in that hee hath given mee ſome meaſure of ability and grace to doe ſome thing: but likewiſe, that I may alwaies as juſtly ſay, as he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my deſire is at this preſent, that whatſoever thing hee putteth in my hands to doe, may be done princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, or much rather, in obedience to him of whom I receive both the will and the deed; and ſecondarily, to make the beſt uſe thereof I can, both for my ſelfe and others, then any wiſe to affect ſingularity, either by the
<pb facs="tcp:17599:6"/> raritie of the project it ſelfe (in thinking it matchleſſe, or that it cannot be ſurmatched) or yet ſo much as by meanes thereof to claime any periſhing title, preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or preheminence at all which may not juſtly be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed unto the inſtrumentall, or any wiſe derogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the <hi>principall efficient</hi> of what is done.</p>
            <p>Concerning the elements and contemplations of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, whereby may be conſidered and obſerved the definitions, derivations, and diviſions of the Arte, cauſes and occaſions of the practiſe: I intend not much to inſiſt in this firſt part, neither yet of the excellencie of writing in reſpect of the renowne, neceſſitie, utilitie, raritie, antiquity, univerſality, and noble diſcent ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; becauſe they are already illuſtrated in the ſecond part, for onely the principles are briefly expreſſed here, but the reaſons and uſe of all largely diſcuſſed there.</p>
            <p>Therefore, to be ſhort in what I intend to ſay in this Preface to the commendation of <hi>writing</hi> (neither for want of matter nor cauſe, but rather for brevitie, and to ſhun repetition) I hope any of any breeding, will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe, that by the bleſſing of God upon the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes of <hi>writing,</hi> (which it pleaſed himſelf, both as our bleſſed Creator and Redeemer to practiſe, and which all Emperours, Kings, Monarchs, Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and Gentles muſt, though they ſhould practiſe no other art) we have not onely his bleſſed word written for our learning, that it may be a lanterne to our feete, and a light unto our pathes, both to direct us in the way of life, and how to ſhun the ſnares of death,</p>
            <p>But likewiſe thereby all high matters, of whatſoever nature or importance, are both intended &amp; proſecuted, ſecret matters are ſecretly kept, friends that be a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand miles diſtant are conferred with, and (after a ſort) viſited, the excellent workes of godly men, the grave ſentences of wiſe men, and the profitable arts of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, who died a thouſand yeeres agoe, are yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant for our daily uſe and imitation; all the eſtates, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, cities, and countries of the world are governed,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:7"/> Lawes and Printing maintained, juſtice and diſcipline adminiſtred, youth bred in pietie, vertue, manners and learning at ſchooles and Vniverſities, and that which is both moſt and beſt, all the Churches of God from the beginning eſtabliſhed, and alwaies unto this day edified, yea and will be to the end of the world, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all and whatſoever to the contrary is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intented, or can be proſecuted.</p>
            <p>But if any ſhould demand how theſe prerogatives of writing doe belong to Expedition, and exact teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to write?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, by reaſoning thus,</p>
            <p>Vnder the generall of every thing, all the ſpecials thereof are included.</p>
            <p>But Expedition and exactneſſe of teaching to write, are ſpecials of writing.</p>
            <p>Therefore Expedition and exactneſſe of teaching to write, are included under the generall of <hi>writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propoſition hath alwaies beene a principle in reaſon, and therefore is a thing moſt evident.</p>
            <p>The aſſumption may be cleared, firſt thus.</p>
            <p n="1">1 If the knowledge, uſe and benefit of writing be excellent, rare, and pretious, then the teaching thereof muſt alſo be ſo.</p>
            <p>But the former is manifeſt, therefore the latter will follow by true conſequence. Secondly thus:</p>
            <p n="2">2 Teaching to write, is uſefull and commendable, therefore Expedition in teaching to write, muſt alſo be uſefull and commendable.</p>
            <p>The antecedent is already ſhowne, and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent plainely followeth. And thirdly,</p>
            <p n="3">3 Expedition is very uſefull and commendable, not onely in reſpect of the eaſineſſe and readineſſe of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and learning by meanes thereof, But likewiſe, of the encouragement of the learners, and that both by ſparing their time and labours; and conſequently ſo much the leſſe hindering their other affaires, by how much theſe rules of art and method here profeſſed, be
<pb facs="tcp:17599:7"/> more exact, eaſie, and ready then any heretofore either taught or publiſhed.</p>
            <p>And if any ſhould alledge, that many have taught to write both before theſe rules were knowne, and doe alſo teach yet without the knowledge of them, both ſpeedily and well enough.</p>
            <p>To whom alſo I anſwer at length, and by occaſion therof doe inſiſt in divers particulars, which although they may ſeeme alſo at the firſt view not to agree, well enough to the point in hand, yet they doe ſerve greatly for illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, and are rather a tranſition to further probation, then any wiſe a digreſſion, which may be as eaſily proved, as that which is immediately proved, if need ſo required.</p>
            <p>How many ſoever doe try or eſſay to doe any rare thing, that their action of trying or eſſaying, doth not prove the ſpeedy nor well-doing of the thing, (which if I doe not (in what I profeſſe) I doe nothing) for it is one thing to doe, and another thing to doe ſpeedily, and the third thing to doe well; betweene the firſt and ſecond, or yet the third, there is many times no leſſe difference, then betweene a Maſter and a Diſciple; and all the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene what I profeſſe, and that which others doe, is that I thus endeavour to adde two words to mine, of which they are negligent in procuring to theirs, and theſe are <hi>Speedily and well:</hi> To the which two words, if I ſhould reduce all my profeſſion, it would follow by good enough conſequence, that that man is very uncapable, that cannot learne from one that is ſo careful to teach, thoſe two words in ſixe houres time; yet I have more fully expreſſed theſe two in twelve words, which doe containe the ſubſtance of all words that can bee either ſpoken or written for our good, all the letters of the Alphabet, and all the curious ſtrokes of joyning, and that for the ſpeed and eaſe of all learners; which therefore if they once can doe, they may write what other matter or words they pleaſe, of that hand which they ſo learne. But to returne to our point, the greateſt approbation ſtandeth in this that followeth, how many ſoever doe a thing as well as poſſibly they can, if
<pb facs="tcp:17599:8"/> there be yet one that excelleth them all, then will not his doing be ſo much the more in requeſt, by how many have tryed either before him, or in his dayes to doe it? Whereas if but one or a few try to doe a thing, (as it were) in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, it will be ſo much the leſſe reſpected, by how much it is leſſe knowne, tryed or approved.</p>
            <p>We ſee when a ſtrong man (to try his ſtrength) doth throw a double canon bullet alone, and caſteth it further at the laſt, then at the firſt, doth over match no man, but himſelfe, and not himſelfe neither, becauſe the difference doth conſiſt in the circumſtance of time, and not of perſon, in that he caſteth it further at one time then at another, by his further practiſe, and longer experiment, for he ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth the ſame man.</p>
            <p>But to draw this point to ſome further length, if many have tryed their ſtrength and skill before him, yea, and the furtheſt marke ſet up by any who have had the vantguard formerly, whether he or any of all the reſt, ſhall yet be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reached by ſome other unexpected, then is his ſtrength and skill diſcovered, that tryed laſt, and ſo much the more both reſpected and manifeſted, by how much hee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reached all that have tryed ſince the firſt.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if that wherein any doth excell many, and yet not all, be thus regarded, and that either for ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of ability, and dexterity in the doing, or in regard of the time or place of the action, for poſſibly either ſome one or other elſewhere could have matched what was done there at that time, or elſe ſome living in the ſame place at another time. Then what greater reſpect ſhall be had to any profitable or vertuous worke that any one ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould both begin and accompliſh alone, which none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in any age or nation ever ſo much as imagined?</p>
            <p>Herein doth ſingularity moſt conſiſt, if by any it might be as lawfully affected, as it is needful by all to be rejected.</p>
            <p>I could give many inſtances, and of divers ſorts, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how ſome famous and rare men in all ages have beene excellent in many things above all others in the age wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they have lived; ſome in ſome things, and others in
<pb facs="tcp:17599:8"/> other things, yea, and ſome alſo in ſome things, which none either before or after them have done, (which is correſpondent to what was ſpoken laſt) but becauſe I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect brevity, howſoever I be driven againſt my inclination and diſpoſition, to the other extremitie, (even as well to be on my guard for all oppoſers, and to give every one his due, as to ſatisfie all learners, and to give each one his part;) I will make choiſe therefore to ſpeake of thoſe things which have beene in theſe dayes, becauſe they are moſt in remembrance, or beſt knowne to many yet living, moſt pregnant to our preſent purpoſe, moſt forcible to prove the poſſibility of what is intended, and both moſt probable and credible to all of this age, ſince they have all come to paſſe therein.</p>
            <p>Many godly, wiſe, learned, and valiant men, both En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh and Scottiſh, hath Britaine brought forth, even in the ſame age wherein we live, who have excelled many that have beene before them in many ages, whoſe names were tedious to expreſſe, and their workes a thouſand fold more tedious to declare in any competent meaſure; but both their matchleſſe fame (in thoſe things wherein they ſurmatched others) and their magnificke workes beare witneſſe of their perſons, who now reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>I would gladly begin here at the higheſt degree, and expreſſe both ſome particular matter and cauſe of true and well deſerved praiſe due unto that ſtate, but eſpecially to a happy and late Poſſeſſor thereof, were it not that I am commanded by modeſty to ceaſe, therefore onely thus much.</p>
            <p>If there were any univerſall Chronicles royall, the moſt renowned memory of King <hi>James</hi> for his matchleſſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and learning, might not onely be recorded in great Capitall and text lines, with letters both of pure gold, and perfect ſilver, but likewiſe ſet with rich Diamonds and Pearle, and flouriſhed in moſt curious manner, with all colours of inke, before all Kings ſince the dayes of good King <hi>Ioſias;</hi> but ſuch a one as I, neither being able in any
<pb facs="tcp:17599:9"/> meaſure to expreſſe, nor yet any booke of this kinde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to comprehend what commendation hee as Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument (in uſing of his gifts) deſerved, I think it moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to deſiſt, and goe to others of inferiour degree.</p>
            <p>Yet onely theſe few I will name, with their rare and commendable acts ſo briefly, as the ſufficiencie of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and equitie of the cauſe doe require, and as there may be any impreſſion left to the Reader or Hearer hereof, whereby, if they pleaſe, to enquire further of thoſe things, which were done by theſe worthy Inſtruments, whom it pleaſed God to raiſe up for his owne glory, and the good of his Church.</p>
            <p>Onely theſe five I will name, the firſt is Maſter <hi>William Perkins,</hi> becauſe hee was one of the firſt in this age, that tooke extraordinary paines in writing many excellent and learned Bookes, both for the benefit and eaſe of all that either wrote or taught ſince, or yet learned for their owne uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And to the intent hee might ſo much the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what he had reſolved in this matter, hee did mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate both his dyet and ſleepe according to the ſhortneſſe of his time, and neceſſitie of his calling: for he not onely (almoſt every day of his pilgrimage in this life, after he was any wiſe enlightned and enabled) was marvellous diligent and temperate, but likewiſe in the night time he had a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice tyed about his necke, which after hee had ſlept foure houres time, gave him a checke, by meanes whereof hee wakened, that (after he had ſtroken fire) he might either reade, write, pray, or meditate two or three houres, many times before any of the houſe (whitherſoever hee ſojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) went to their buſineſſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is Maſter <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> who both wrote very much, and learnedly, and lived very modeſtly: yea and had no more for a long time, but eight pence a weeke.</p>
            <p>The third is Maſter <hi>George Buchanan;</hi> who had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be Tutor to our late Soveraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> of famous memory; although many in divers nations both before him, and in his dayes, have tryed to tranſlate the Pſalmes of <hi>David</hi> in latine verſe, yet never any of their tranſlations were thought comparable to <hi>Buchanans</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17599:9"/> Pſalmes. And by reaſon thereof, and of ſome other rare workes, and that hee was ſo happy an inſtrument of the breeding of ſuch a worthy Monarch, whom all the world admired for his wiſedome and learning; his fame is very great among all the godly learned in Europe, and ſo much the greater, both becauſe he was a great traveller, and that his bookes are diſperſed in all nations.</p>
            <p>The fourth is Maſter <hi>Iames Creighton,</hi> who being a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron in <hi>Scotland,</hi> chooſed rather to travell in forraigne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and follow his learning, then to ſtay at home and enjoy his Patrimony. Concerning whom, though I bee ſomewhat large, I hope it ſhall not ſeeme tedious; howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever many have taken great paines both to attaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to invent the art of memory (to be a helpe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto yet this yong Noble man was matchleſſe in both, and that not onely in his youth-hood at home, but likewiſe in all his travels abroad, yea &amp; ſcarcely doth any hiſtory make mention of any the like before him: and beſides, which is no leſſe worthy conſideration, it is reported (by men of great worth and credit, who are yet alive, and knew his education) that he was never taught, at leaſt after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner in ſtudying by booke; onely he ſometimes heard what was taught to others, and ſeldome either read or ſtudied, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather (beſides the appointed times of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation) he had liberty procured of thoſe who hearing of his fame, came both farre and neare to viſit and try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or not ſuch things were, according to the report, when in the meane time all the reſt of his condiſciples were kept in at their ſtudies, and that both when he was at Schooles and Vniverſities.</p>
            <p>After he had thus paſt his courſe, and came to be made Maſter of Arts, (as they are called there) ſcarcely any could be found to diſpute againſt his Theſes in publike. Leaſt they ſhould incurre any diſgrace before ſuch a learned au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, and that from ſuch a young S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>holler, for his fame being ſo ſpread throughout all the land, there was a greater aſſembly of the learned in the Vniverſitie of S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> at that time, then was either many y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers before, or y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb facs="tcp:17599:10"/> ſince, in the time of any laureation.</p>
            <p>Having paſt his degree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in his travels, and upon the manifold experiences which he had of his owne ability at home, whither ſoever he came, and heard of any publike declamation or diſputation, there, or any where, he alwaies addveſſed himſelfe thither againſt the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, if either diſtance of place, or other urgent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did not hinder him. And amongſt many other places wherein he purchaſt great commendation, he being once at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (as ſome doe thinke, and others doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it was at <hi>Padua,</hi> but whereſoever it was, the action is moſt certaine, becauſe it was his ordinatie practiſe any where,) and there being a very great aſſembly of the moſt learned of that part of the world, and a moſt pregnant and rare man having declamed an excellent Oration, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained greater applauſe then many others of a long time; Maſter <hi>Creighton</hi> (being very attentive before his face all the while, and unknowne almoſt to any) asked licence, although a ſtranger, to ſpeake a few words againſt him who had laſt ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (alledging that that aſſembly being like a proclaimed Fayre, to which all ſtrangers were invited, and none exempted, but each one free both to buy ſuch wares as they ſhould need, and to ſell ſuch as they have to ſpare;) which being granted, he began thus: This is a very learned man, ſaith hee, but he hath his learning, as many have their riches, even by reaping the fruits of other mens labours. If this hath beene his practiſe heretofore, I know not, but one thing I know well, all that he hath ſpoken now, is that which I was minded to ſpeake, by what meanes he hath got the copie thereof, I am not yet certain, but to be ſhort, I will prove that it is mine, and not his, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all this honourable Auditorie, thus: firſt, I will repeat all and whatſoever he hath ſpoken, verbatim: ſecondly, ſhew him where he failed in ſuch things: thirdly, ſhew how he and all others may prevent the like errour henceforth: and laſtly, reſume all in a few heads, and raiſe ſome obſervations thereupon. Which hee did at great length according to the method laid downe, and was both
<pb facs="tcp:17599:10"/> heard with farre greater attention then the firſt ſpeaker, and received ten times greater applauſe then he did.</p>
            <p>The other ſpeaker being aſtonied and ſilenced all this time, and yet keeping his pulpit, which was ſo much the more griefe unto him, by how much he was the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous to the eyes of all, his caſe ſo ſuddenly altering, yea and turning quite contrary to what it was an houre or two before; for the affront or defeat which hee received then, did countervaile all his applauſe immediately before.</p>
            <p>At length, Maſter <hi>Creighton</hi> having finiſhed what hee was to ſpeake, and all the people earneſtly looking what iſſue would come of all theſe proceedings, and hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the countenance of the other ſpeaker all the while to be a little altered, deſired him to take courage againe, for he would tell him ſuch good newes, as might be a meanes both to revive his ſpirit, and reſtore him to his former hopes of preferment, yea and alſo to the favour of all thoſe that might preferre him, which hee did after this manner. He not onely confeſſed publikely, that the ſpeaker was a very learned man, and worthy of ſuch promotion as was expected at that time, (which notwithſtanding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe might have had, and farre greater too, (both there &amp; in many other places) if he had either loved preferment for learning, better then learning it ſelfe, or yet the favour of great men, who both loved him ſo dearely, and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him ſo greatly, that almoſt they made him their equall whereſoever he went.</p>
            <p>But likewiſe he acknowledged that all which was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, was the ſpeakers owne worke, and no part thereof his, more then the obſervations which he in publike made ſo abruptly by occaſion thereof: for it pleaſed God to give him ſuch an excellent gift of memory to adorne his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that he could hardly forget any thing whatſoever he either read, ſaw, or heard; and withall he proteſted, that what he did, was not to doe harme to any man, nor yet to extenuate or undervalue any mans gifts, of what meaſure ſoever, but rather to encourage, and doe good to all, by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering unto them the benefit of what he received, and that
<pb facs="tcp:17599:11"/> he might declare what was ſpoken amiſſe: which hee did ſo much the rather, becauſe the ſame was ſo farre from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceived by any of the moſt pregnant in all that great aſſembly, that ſome did approve by their applauſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by their ſilence, even that, as well as any thing that was ſpoken: for he conſidered that things ſo publikely ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, ought either to be publikely approved, by ſilence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found good, or (after licence given) to bee publikely reproved by contradicting, if they be otherwiſe; to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that God might be glorified in whatſoever gifts he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth upon men, and all his people truely informed by the uſe thereof in all things, and ſo none to depart in doubt of any thing delivered.</p>
            <p>Moſt of his rare workes with the times, places, cauſes, and occaſions thereof, are largely comprehended in the Duke of <hi>Manto</hi> his records, with whom he ſpent moſt of his dayes, and in a booke dedicated to himſelfe by one <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius</hi> a learned Italian, who having either converſed with him in his travels, or being an eye witneſſe to many of his proceedings, giveth him greater commendation then hath beene given to any, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, who had the extraordinary gifts of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>The fift and laſt is <hi>John Naper,</hi> who was father to my Lord of <hi>Merchiſton</hi> that now is: he was reported to bee one of the moſt painefull and learned Divines that hath beene of any Noble man theſe many yeeres; and beſides many other his rare workes, wherein he was moſt labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (even when he was grievouſly diſeaſed with the Gout for divers yeeres together, which is ſo much the greater commendation to him, by how much it might have beene an excuſe to others) he was one of the firſt and chiefeſt in our dayes that tooke exceſſive paines day and night, to bring the booke of the <hi>Revelat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> to be ſo well underſtood and taught, as God be praiſed it is at this day: (for this I know, being his neighbour a long time at <hi>Edenborough,</hi> (though I had neither the happineſſe to bee acquainted with him, nor to be capable of his worth) his candle went never out (I thinke) ſo long as his breath was in,) for he
<pb facs="tcp:17599:11"/> conſidering the title thereof to be <hi>the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>velation of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and finding a bleſſing pronounced to all thoſe that reade, heare, and practiſe the ſame, did ſpend moſt of his daies in labouring to diſcover the myſterie of that moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and profound Prophecie, that it might be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in ſome meaſure by all unto whom it was ſent, and ſo much the rather, that as the Holy Spirit is the firſt love-token or earneſt of our ſalvation, ſo the <hi>Revelation</hi> is the laſt love-token, that our Saviour hath ſent to his Church, till he himſelfe returne.</p>
            <p>By reaſon whereof, how many ſoever hath written, ſince <hi>Merchiſton</hi> did write, and it may bee hath ſeene farther then he, which he himſelfe would alſo have done, if he had lived longer as well as they, (and which doth appeare in that his owne laſt edition, ſo farre excelleth the firſt) yet he being ſuch a wiſe, learned, and excellent guide, in going before, and pathing (or at leaſt greatly helping to path) the way (as it were in a morning, throw great heapes of ſnow) unto all that have walked ſince, by his ſo exquiſite labours, even his paraphraſes of this kinde, is more worthy (I ſay) of commendation in that reſpect at leaſt, then any who have yet ſucceeded him, for they have had all his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be a light (under God) to them, but he had none of theirs to helpe him. And therefore as his name was <hi>Na-peir,</hi> both after the Scottiſh pronuntiation and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo it may be juſtly called <hi>No-peere,</hi> according to the Engliſh: It is the fame which hee hath left, that maketh his name to be great, for he is yet called there, as (I thinke) he may be to the worlds end, either here, or any where, <hi>Matchleſſe</hi> MERCHISTON <hi>Mathematitian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If all the names ſhould bee inſerted here, of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and valiant men (ſuch as King <hi>Robert Bruce,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Wallace)</hi> with all their matchleſſe acts, and all the remarkable deeds of others in other ages, who have beene greatly renowned in that moſt renowned kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (which I have the honour to call the land of my nativitie) and not thoſe few examples in this age, as well of that, as of this worthy kingdome wherein now I live,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:12"/> choſen for all, to ſhew that any man is ſo much the better, yea, and the more to be hoped and expected of what hee can doe, in that he hath beene borne or bred there, but far more both, doubtleſſe it might fill as great a volume as the Romane Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>And if it be thus unto ſuch there, it will follow alſo in time, to be ſo unto the like here, and that becauſe they are both of Britaine, and ſo both not onely of one continent, and of one name, but likewiſe are now both under one head, and of one Religion, yea and hath both one kinde of languag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and one forme of writing, and that which crowneth all, they do all ſtrive to love one another, as they doe themſelves.</p>
            <p>THVS, leaving the commendation of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, who have excelled all others in the things whereof they were excellent, I will ſpeake ſomewhat of the honour of that renowned kingdome, which chiefly conſiſts in the prerogatives or priviledges thereof, with thy leave and patience, diligent Reader, &amp; without derogation to any other kingdome, which hath either greater honour or prerogatives, or better priviledges of other kindes, or yet is of greater worth of it ſelfe; after I have ſhewed ſome differences betweene that nation, people, and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof, and others who challenge a higher place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of ſome greater reſpects: all which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doe, I hope no judicious man will finde that I digreſſe any wiſe from the point, who will but conſider with me, that whatſoever things are in the way of any thing, have alwaies ſome relation to the end thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they leade thereunto, and that ſome impe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ments al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo muſt be removed out of the way hereof, which doe greatly hinder the paſſage to the end, that the worke may the more eaſily proceed.</p>
            <p>For ſince the probability of the poſſibility of this taske is my part at this time, I muſt firſt uſe ſuch lawfull ordinarie meanes, as I know will make way unto the performance thereof, and then thoſe, which will fully accompliſh the thing expected. And if it be needfull that the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:17599:12"/> we ayme at any thing be wiſhed and laboured for, by all thoſe who deſire that thing, then doubtleſſe to ſhew both the poſſibility of attaining, and probability or certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of attaining thereof, muſt alſo be needfull, and that not for the undertaker alone, but for all who would partake of the benefit as well as he, and eſpecially thoſe who are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubtfull or miſtruſtfull, and therefore ſlacke in uſing of the meanes, that they alſo being in ſome meaſure ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well as others, may with the more courage, intend, begin, proceed, and proſecute as well as others.</p>
            <p>But although the nature of many things, both ſpoken, and to be ſpoken here, doth not agree ſtrictly to writing it ſelfe, yet if they be well conſidered largely, they doe ſerve greatly both to ſhew the poſſibility of ſo ſpeedy teaching to write, and to make way to the probabilitie thereof, by ſhewing that there be ſome men of one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that be farre more generous and compleately both bred, qualified or gifted, yea and can take greater paines to put all to a good uſe, then all thoſe of another kingdome, who are moſt pregnant in any facultie of this kinde. To the intent it may appeare, that from thoſe excellent preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, which may juſtly be attributed to the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in generall, whereof I am to ſpeake, and eſpecially to the head thereof as the fountaine, there may be ſome iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of excellencie derived to every particular member of the ſame, above thoſe who cannot claime unto the like, as both divine and other hiſtories doe ſpecifie, what great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge it was to be a Romane.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe, it is needfull that thoſe prerogatives and priviledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be here expreſſed for another ſpeciall reſpect, yet tending to make way to the ſame end and purpoſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for preventing or removing a prejudicate opinion which ſome of the vulgar ſort, have againſt the famous kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that without any ground or reaſon, inſomuch as though one like <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhould come forth thereof to this place, yet they were wont more often then now, thus to demand, Can any good thing come out of <hi>Scotland?</hi> doth it afford this or that? doe ſuch and
<pb facs="tcp:17599:13"/> ſuch things grow there? doe any ſuch learned men, or faire writers live there, as there be here? and many the like idle queſtions, which be rather moved for deriſion, then any wiſe to require reſolution.</p>
            <p n="1">1 But all ſuch kinde of perſons were fully anſwered, and confuted, both in thoſe, and in all other ſuch things: for not onely it pleaſed God, that one like <hi>Salomon</hi> came out thereof indeed, &amp; removed all ſuch queſtions, as the bright ſunne doth expell the miſty clouds, and did put to ſilence all ſuch perſons (at leaſt their impud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncie and frequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncie in thoſe things) and that both by ſhewing them the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of what they pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded, or would have had, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch a combination betweene them, and thoſe of whom they ſpake, that the like was never formerly in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: ſo that many of both nations, who were diverſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected before, have reſpected others as their owne moſt affectioned and deare brethren (both at home and abroad) afterwards, and for the moſt part, ever ſince? But another alſo hath come forth thereof, God bleſſe him, (like <hi>Joſias)</hi> who can both repreſſe all ſuch frivolous queſtions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe all thoſe who will offer to propound them any more.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Abundance and varietie of all commodities doe both come out of <hi>Scotland</hi> daily hither, by ſea and land, and goe every where abroad, (as have alwaies in all ages) which doe manifeſt the plentifull increaſe thereof. If ſome parts of that land may be called barren, it is but in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts; even as the moſt fruitfull kingdome cannot be all alike fruitfull; for there was a hill country in the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> it ſelfe, for beſtiall, as well as valley or dale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ground for corn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; yea and doubtleſſe there be ſome ſpeciall parts alſo of it, as good as the beſt parts of other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the value of the commodities which thoſe parts doe afford, being accounted according to the valuation of the places, where they come to be in greateſt requeſt, like as other kingdomes doe with the commodities which they yeeld.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The worthy people of that ancient kingdome, doe
<pb facs="tcp:17599:13"/> live with ſuch plenty of all ſorts of things at home amongſt themſelves, as they need not yeeld nor give place, to any people or nation for any thing, more then they need to doe unto them: and therefore although mutuall traffique or exchange of commodities be no diſparagement (I hope) but rather a great credit, as well as an advancement to any people of whatſoever kingdome: yet they could as well (at leaſt) ſubſiſt without the ſame, (if there were cauſe, as I hope there ſhall never be) yea and live both as conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly and modeſtly with their owne, as any people in the world.</p>
            <p>If at any time, eſpecially in the yeeres of famine, when it pleaſeth God moſt juſtly to afflict them, as he doth their neighbour countries, (either then, or at other times) they be forced to buy ſuch things as they need, from other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as Gods people of old did of Egypt, they pay them as well for what they receive, as other nations doe when they buy ſuch things (as they need) of them, upon the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, either of neceſſitie or extremitie. And if none be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove any thing to the contrary of thoſe things, then why doe not all acknowledge them to be true?</p>
            <p>Whereby (in the meane time as it hath beene alwaies) it is moſt evident (although there were no more to be ſaid) that that kingdome is a moſt compleate kingdome, and both as plentifull and able to ſerve the owne turne, as any other kingdome is to ſerve it ſelfe: And therefore no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion ought to be made (by any whoſoever) neither of the plentie nor abilitie thereof, more then of any other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, neither in ſport to maintaine table diſcourſe, nor yet in earneſt purpoſe for curioſitie, at other times or occaſions.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who doe enjoy a better land, are bound to be ſo much the more thankfull to him, who is the true owner of the whole earth, and all that therein is, to diſpoſe unto what people ſoever he will; which dutie if they doe not carefully diſcharge, they will be ſo much the more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable in the day of retribution, when they are called to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for violent poſſeſſion thereof: and wee are taught,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:14"/> taught, both by his word and daily experience, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll as by hiſtories, how often the Monarchies and Kingdomes of the world are tranſlated from one people unto another, and all through ingratitude and impenitencie.</p>
            <p>And whereas it may be thought, that ſome other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes being more fruitfull, are therefore more able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the neceſſities of that kingdome, then it is to helpe them; yet if the varietie, extent, and worth of all things which it ſendeth yeerely to other kingdomes, above what any king ſome ſendeth it, be well weighed, eſteemed, and conſidered, none of them can ſurmatch it, yea ſcarcely compare with it in any degree, howſoever many doe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the greater part of it. But how this defect thereof, in reſpect of other kingdomes, and yet the compleatneſſe or equalitie of it with the beſt of them, can agree in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; ſince onely, but ſome parts thereof, can match the beſt parts of them, (and yet nevertheleſſe hath as great plenty in the generall, both to ſerve it ſelfe within, and to furniſh others without, as any of them) thoſe two effects doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of theſe two cauſes (or ſuppliments two manner of waies) the one principall, and the other ſecondarie.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt or principall, doth proceed of the bleſſing of God, which in the midſt of outward povertie, maketh riches to increaſe, as the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> though of it ſelfe farre inferiour to other lands, both in quantitie and fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet ſo long as his people had their reſidence there, it did flow with milke and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ney, and ſuſtained at one time, eighteene hundred thouſand fighting men, both beſides the tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and what it ſpared alſo to ſend abroad to other nations; yea and all the mightie Kings and Iudges thereof in more ſumptuous manner, many times, then any Monarches ever were before, or after them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond, of the vertuous induſtrie of the people of that kingdome, which may bee well compared with the induſtrie of the moſt excellent people of whatſoever king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (although they have both greater matter whereof, and a better ſubject whereon to worke.) The firſt world had almoſt all things without labour, which fertile king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb facs="tcp:17599:14"/> doe yet imitate, that they may have the more time to vice, as they had: but the commendable people of the famous kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> doe ſurpaſſe all fertile king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in labour and induſtrie, both early and late, yea and ſweating of all the body, as well as the forehead, according to the ordinance of God, pronounced upon the diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our firſt Parents.</p>
            <p>In citie labour, or artificer worke, yea or coſening by trade, they delight not to be ſo expert, as ſome people of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kingdomes are, neither to maintaine unneceſſarie trades, or ſuch as any wiſe tend, or be more inclinable to vice then vertue, nor to ſell ſlight or counterfeit wares, under colour of good and upright; nor yet are they any wiſe ſo bold either to praiſe their owne wares (at home nor abroad) nor to invite (farre leſſe take hold of) cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, as they paſſe the ſtreets upon other buſineſſes, to come in, and buy their wares: but as for the moſt part, they are every way both more conſcionable and modeſt, ſo many of them likewiſe have all needfull things, both as cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and farre more ſubſtantious to ſell, unto ſuch onely as doe offer to buy, then any others elſewhere.</p>
            <p>Their obedience to the true God and Chriſt whom hee hath ſent, and to their ſuperiours, with their commendable induſtrie, and conſcionable carriage; yea and their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet ſpending on food and apparrell, according to their degree (with other reſpects which may be gathered from other particulars following) are the cauſes, doubtleſſe, that it hath pleaſed God to keepe that worthy native people together, as the true of spring of the firſt planters of that land, though alwaies ſending multitudes upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to helpe other nations, even unto this day, when al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the world hath turned upſide downe.</p>
            <p>So the matchleſſe induſtrie, ſrugalitie, care, and labour of that moſt vertuous people, is the ſecondarie cauſe of their equalitie of maintenance with the people of other kingdomes (both to ſpend and ſend) or the ſuppliment of any defect of fruitfulneſſe in that kingdome.</p>
            <p>Which conſiſts rather in carefull, diligent, and timely
<pb facs="tcp:17599:15"/> manuring the ground, (both before and after the ſowing of the ſeed) attending their beſtiall, and in making all kinde of cloth, as well linnen as woollen; which according to the commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able practiſe both of <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of King <hi>Salomon, Dorcas,</hi> and other both Noble and religious women, is the laudable exerciſe alſo of all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and grave wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, throughout the moſt part of that kingdome, as well Citie as Country, and that to ſerve their owne families, to give unto thoſe that ſtand in ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and either to ſell at home, or ſend abroad in exchange for oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r wares. But they doe not eſteem vertue to conſiſt in citie induſtrie, yea or ſcarcely any thing done with the needle, worthy of the name of worke, except onely the making of needfull and comely apparrell; for howſoever it be thought by others elſewhere, to bee vertuous, yet by them, it is either frivolous or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idiculous, or for the moſt part idle or vicious, becauſe it maintaineth both: yea and the women there, are ſo grave, ſhamefaſt, and modeſt, yea and ſo farre from following new faſhions, either by changing with the winde, commonly every weeke, or with the Moone ſurely every moneth, that they keepe the very ſur-name they have of their father, as well as their chriſten-name, even from their birth to their death, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome obſerved, for the moſt part, in other nations.</p>
            <p>Thus it is apparent by their practiſe, that theſe being the three chiefe, and moſt commendable points of civill vertue, are therefore to bee embraced, and all others that are either repugnant, or not agreeable to any of theſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are ſubordinate to ſerve or maintaine all, or any of them, nor yet the actors or inſtruments thereof in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (ſpiritually nor civilly) can hardly come within the compaſſe of laudable vertue; but rather are, (as they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies have beene) procuring cauſes to draw downe Gods inevitable judgements upon Kingdomes, Nations, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Cities.</p>
            <p>All vertuous Citizens that doe live in a lawfull calling, whither they procure much or little by their honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:17599:15"/> induſtrie, are hereby commended, in that they are under theſe three ſorts comprehended; and in a moſt ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all manner thoſe that are moſt eminent, by their commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble workes, as well for the common wealth, as their owne particular or private reſpects, ſuch as either Maſter <hi>Sutton,</hi> or Maſter <hi>Middleton</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> or Maſter <hi>Heriot</hi> at <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And againe, as it is ſaid of a ſtrong man, that he can live any where, according to that Proverbe, <hi>Omne ſolum forti patria;</hi> ſo it may be juſtly ſaid of Scottiſh men, that they can live in any part of the world (whither it be inhabited or not) for as they are both moſt curious and deſirous to travell in all nations for attaining of languages, manners, and for ſupplying of whatſoever defects in their breeding at home, that they may be complete men, as the land of their nativity, is a complete land; ſo they are moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of any people, I thinke in the world, whereſoever they travel or reſort, for not only the nobler or more gentle ſort are meete for any rare enterpriſe of great worth: But likewiſe the inferiours are bred either to ſome Art or profeſſion at home before they come forth, or to put their hand to any kinde of ordinary worke, &amp; to comport with whatſoever kinde of entertainement or lodging, yea and to beare with the diſpoſitions of any kinde of people, according to reaſon and diſcretion: whereas thoſe that come ſhort either in all thoſe or moſt of them, and yet will travell, would doe better to ſtay at home, and either keepe the Tongs at the fire ſide, or looke to the Geeſe about the dores.</p>
            <p>By conſideration of which premiſſes before and after ſpecified, it may be eaſily obſerved, that a plantation of Scottiſh men in any fertile kingdome, doth farre excell ſo many in number as doe come from any other kingdome unto that ſoyle; as we may eaſily perceive what great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, labour and induſtrie, they of the Scottiſh nation have made in the north, yea or worſt parts of the kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> both above the natives, &amp; others of the Southern, beſt, and moſt choiſeſt places of the whole land: if withall
<pb facs="tcp:17599:16"/> wee will carefully account, or duely reſpect the great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or inequality of the places. And by conſequence hereof, it may be obſerved, at leaſt ſuppoſed, that if a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were indifferently choſen, in <hi>Scotland,</hi> brought forth thence, and placed in any kingdome more fertile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then it, and as many country men of that kingdome, ſent thither in their places, ſurely it might be well expected, that the one would make ſuch a vertuous and honeſt ſhift to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the ground, and live without any ſupply at all (but Gods alſufficient providence) whereas it might be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that the other would ſtarve and die, if they were not both better and more ſpeedily ſupplied, then all the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie they could uſe, whereby to live.</p>
            <p>And to come to an eaſier and nearer tryall, we both ſee here, and it is knowne every where, when any generous, or laborious Scottiſh man is equally matched to worke, toyle, eate, drinke, ſleepe, travell, yea or fight with any ſuch as himſelfe (by appearance) of any oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rland, it is ten to one, if he hold not out, and prevaile, when the other ſhall die or give over; which as it is a ſpeciall cauſe that Scottiſh men are generally and univerſally as well accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and priviledged, as almoſt the natives of any nation, or at leaſt farre better, then ſo many ſuch others of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver other nation: ſo alſo in that they are ſo well beloved every where, is a ſpeciall encouragement for them to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, as ſome of them alwaies doe, ſince whereſoever they ſo journe, they are (for the moſt part) as duely reſpected, yea, and upon as reaſonable termes, as they are in farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant parts from their habitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, friends, and acquaintance in their owne land.</p>
            <p>The ancient Roman priviledge, though it went for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the behalfe of all Romans, throughout all nations, could never in the beſt time thereof, match this peculiar paſſage and generall acceptation of Scottiſh men: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, the Romans did rather claime it as a kinde of homage or obedience due unto them, as being either citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſubjects to the Emperour their head, who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſubdued all nations, then as a thing any wiſe belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:17599:16"/> to them, through their own deſert, or good behaviour: for we ſee that what priviledge, libertie, or toleration ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is taken by compulſion, is not comparable to that which commeth freely by deſerved love, or is given by tender affection.</p>
            <p>I will chooſe two inſtances, which are moſt pregnant to our intended purpoſe, in ſtead of many others of other kindes, which might alſo be alledged, were it not for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie, which will both give farther light to this point, and ſhew that none hath any juſt cauſe to demand, if there bee any learned men, or yet faire writers in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt is, whoſoever ſhall examine the practiſe of learned Scottiſh men, at home, and compare the ſame with ſuch others abroad, in any forraine nation, or yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir practiſe abroad, whereſoever they ſo journe, and doe teach either old or young, and compare the ſame with thoſe of that profeſſion, who be natives in thoſe places, and then they ſhall ſee, that if the fruits of their labours doe not ſurmount all that the natives are able to doe, of that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that land, they ſhall equally match them at leaſt, and beſides give both better attendance, and take greater paines for diſcharge of whatſoever duty they undertake to performe, then they, doe what they can.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And the next is, <hi>Scotland</hi> is ſo farre from being inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to any other kingdome in any thing needfull to the common wealth thereof, that it is rather ſuperiour to all kingdomes and nations; for it hath ſuch a neare relation to every nation under the ſunne, that almoſt there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable art nor profeſſion any where, but either it, or the like is taught, profeſſed, and practiſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> either in Schooles or Vniverſities; or elſe ſome Scottiſh man or other, can compaſſe the way, or finde out the meanes whereby to attaine both to the knowledge and practiſe of it; howſoever (by the way) I have heard it often deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (among other queſtions) whether or no, there be any Vniverſities there? but I have anſwered, twiſe ſo many as be here: although it were as rare, or excellent an Arte, as the Phoenix is a bird, (that cannot live ſo farre north)
<pb facs="tcp:17599:17"/> yet <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelfe is both as rare, and farre more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yea and hath many hundreth yeeres longer ſubſiſted (God be praiſed) than ever any Phoenix lived: &amp; as in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling another point by and by ſhall be ſhewed, that in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall reſpects, a more excellent and magnifique king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was never.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time to end this point, <hi>Scotland</hi> is ſo farre from yeelding to any other kingdome in any thing, that it will not ſo much as yeeld, in ſo meane a thing as Writing, (which if I be well remembred, is reckoned in the laſt place, among ſuch queſtions as the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doe uſually propound upon all occaſions) ſaving that through modeſty, and entertaining of love, it will rather give place to many kingdomes, than take it from any kingdome at all.</p>
            <p>If any of any kingdome will demand any ſuch queſtion any more, though none of all the men of <hi>Scotland</hi> would daine himſelfe to anſwere it, becauſe it (being ſo frivolous) merits no anſwer, but rather a rebuke, (as I have given to many of the baſer ſort, who have both murmured, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken exception of my Nation, yea and uttered more, then either I will expreſſe, or yet (I thinke) they would avow,) if they ſhould be called to give a reaſon or warrant.</p>
            <p>Surely the moſt rare and curious writs and workes of one woman, <hi>Eſther Engliſh</hi> by name, which are extant both in his Majeſties Librarie at Saint <hi>Iameſes,</hi> and in the Vniverſitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and in many other places elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, may be patternes and examples, as well for practice as teaching, both to all the men and women, profeſſors and others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that either are or have beene in Europe theſe many yeeres; and yet notwithſtanding ſhe would never offer to contend with me in the practiſe, let be in the art, but not onely gave place very freely, after ſome further no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, than ſhe had received at the firſt, eſpecially of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mans ſonne of nine yeeres old, whom I had taught to write a number of hands in moſt excellent manner, who was therefore brought in before the King, as ſhall be ſhewed hereafter: but likewiſe ſhe ever behaved her ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:17599:17"/> very diſcreetly to me, as I alwaies endeavoured both to her, and all others in all things according to my power.</p>
            <p>And beſides her, there bee many excellent Writers in that kingdome, ſuch as theſe (which I doe ſpecifie rather after their age, than either according to their degree or gifts) Maſter <hi>Alexander Paterſon, John Matheſon, Charles Geddy, John Peter, Iames Clarke,</hi> and <hi>Hew Wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce;</hi> ſome whereof are very exquiſite alſo in many other hands than be uſed in Britaine: ſo that in the famous kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſoever ſhould be ſo curious as to ſearch, from men indued with gifts of the higheſt degree, even unto the loweſt, they would both finde, that it is well enough ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with all ſorts of learned and excellent men, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe all needfull and commendable Arts, Sciences, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; and that ſome thereof are as exquiſite, in what they profeſſe, as any of that profeſſion in any other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or nation.</p>
            <p>And therfore the premiſſes being well conſidered, I hope no exception ſhall be any more taken, either of me, or any other of whatſoever degree, in that we have been borne or bred in that kingdome; for if both I and every one ſhould pretermit or paſſe by ſuch aſſertions, or rather aſpertions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the renowne of ſo worthy and famous a kingdome, which by the right of birth, as wel as other reſpects, we are bound to defend, then it would quickly follow that each one would get way, and ſo conſequently in time it might reach very high. And beſides, it is rather a Iewiſh than Chriſtian opinion, to extenuate the commendation of any worthy nation; for the Iewes undervalued the worthy and honourable Citie of <hi>Nazaret,</hi> in that they made queſtion if any good thing could come forth thereof, in reſpect of the other mightie Cities of <hi>Iudea,</hi> wherein belike they more gloried, then glorified God for enjoying of them.</p>
            <p>Then to conclude this point, no prejudicate opinion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any more conceived, no more exception will be any more taken by any, to extenuate whatſoever any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat kingdome hath, which another of another kingdome hath not; and ſo by this meanes and occaſion, not onely the way
<pb facs="tcp:17599:18"/> being rid of all ſuch impediments, to me in this mean par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, it may be the more patent to others in a greater matter: but likewiſe it being proved by the matchleſſe prerogatives of that ancient kingdome, that it is in many reſpects, of incomparable fame, (of which preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives ſo great a number of valorous Kings and their royall acts, recorded in ſo many famous hiſtories, may well bee reckoned in the firſt place, as ſhall be done God willing, by and by, and that our dread Soveraigne, the Kings moſt excellent Majeſtie, their lineall ſucceſſor to raigne over that moſt ancient kingdome, is the moſt renowned, and famous King in the world.</p>
            <p>So, if all theſe weightie reſpects bee well weighed, and duely conſidered, it will follow better thus, then by any other pretended conſequence, that there is rather ſo much the more to be expected of all Scottiſh men, even becauſe they are Scottiſh men, yea and that they are ſo much the more alſo to be reſpected, becauſe they have that due and reſpective honour, title, and prerogative, then if they were of any other kingdome or nation whatſoever; and that by vertue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the honour and excellencie derived from the head to all the body, and ſo to every member thereof: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is one of the chiefe cauſes, why ſo many generous Scottiſh men in their travels almoſt any where, ſave in <hi>England,</hi> neither having lands appropriated unto them, whereby to diſtinguiſh themſelves from others, of inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our qualitie, although perchance diſcended of a worthy and ancient houſe, nor yet any title conferred on them, but onely the <hi>generall,</hi> that they bee Scottiſh men, are prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (both by getting place and preferment) to many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of other nations, who either have lands or other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, (beſides the denomination of their country) yea, and ſometimes both; which is a great cauſe &amp; encouragement for Scottiſh men to travell, as they doe farre more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>But this one thing yet remaineth to be declared, before we proceed to other matter; it is needfull alſo for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding, and ſo in ſome meaſure, making up a
<pb facs="tcp:17599:18"/> compleat ſenſe) both of what hath beene ſaid, and is to be ſpoken to the commendation of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> even to ſhew in what reſpects, it can but compare with the kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> let be with other kingdomes, although theſe ſo joyne together, as that they both make but one continent: yea and doe almoſt lye under one climat and Horizon; which one example ſhall ſuffice to ſhew how <hi>Scotland</hi> may compare with other king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, eſteeming <hi>England</hi> in this comparative reſpect, and many others of other nature, to be as worthy a kingdome (for the quantity) as any in the world. Therefore I will uſe my beſt endeavours, to make a ſhort d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcription of both theſe kingdomes, that the chiefe cauſe may both be ſo much the better, and eaſier perceived: for apparently they will be rather found to appeare in the different uſe of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeverall diſpoſitions, opinions, or practiſes of the inhabitants of either, then in any correſpondencie or equalitie betweene them other wiſe: which compariſon is very worthy obſervation, eſpecially by thoſe who would either learn to be good husbands any where, or yet would conferre or examine their owne private skill, opinion, or practiſe, with the ancient, publike, and approved skill, opinion, and practiſe of thoſe, who have beene both better and longer exerciſed, in all the ſeverall ſorts and degrees of good husbandry.</p>
            <p>The kingdome of <hi>England</hi> is a moſt excellent, pleaſant, and fruitfull land, fairely planted, rarely built, and both well inriched and garniſhed with all ſorts of commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and objects of pleaſure, almoſt like unto <hi>France,</hi> which is (thought to be) the garden of the world.</p>
            <p>It pleaſeth God, that <hi>England</hi> yeeldeth abundance of increaſe, in all things needfull for this mortall life, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe things moſt intended (or beſt liked) by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof, which are indeed (for the moſt part) as civill, modeſt, and loving a people, both among themſelves, and almoſt to all ſtrangers (at home &amp; abroad) yea and as faithfull, true, and obedient ſubjects to our and their dread Soveraigne, as either wee, or any other his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,
<pb facs="tcp:17599:19"/> or yet the ſubjects of any other King, ever were, or can be to any King, Monarch, or Emperour in all the world.</p>
            <p>This fertile kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> bringeth forth as great plenty of all ſorts of graine, and of all kinde of fruits and hearbs, with milke and honey, and all variety and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of other things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both for profit and pleaſure, that mans heart can deſire, for the maintenance and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of naturall life, I thinke as any kingdome whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the bigneſſe thereof, and ſo farre as it is ſowne and laboured: for the inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> almoſt ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſince the dayes of <hi>Engiſt,</hi> of whom both the land and they doe take the name, have thought it farre more eaſie, and no l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe profitable, to reſerve many of the beſt, and moſt fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full places of the land, rather for the entertainment of all ſorts of beſtiall, which they delight more and more yet to have multiplied, than for the bearing or increaſing of Wheate, Barlie, Peaſe, or Beanes; and therefore the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people belike, having greater plenty of all kinde of fleſhes, than of all ſorts of bread, doe chooſe or take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to attribute the generall name <hi>meate,</hi> to fleſh, rather than to bread, or any other kinde of victuals: whether they doe it, becauſe they have it moſt, or love it beſt, or both, is ſomewhat queſtionable, but (notwithſtanding all their induſtry and plenty) one thing is without all queſtion, it remaineth as deare as other things: which is ſomewhat mitigated, both in their higher valuation of money, and greater plenty thereof, than <hi>Scotland</hi> hath at this time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Court lyeth there. I need not to be very prolixe in this deſcription, becauſe I know wherein I am either briefe or deficient, will be well ſupplied by the natives themſelves upon all occaſions, who know their own land better than I, or any other ſtranger, but now wee are all one.</p>
            <p>The kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> beauſe it doth conſiſt as much in hils, as valleyes, and therefore neither altogether ſo fruitfull as <hi>England,</hi> nor yet lyeth ſo hot towards the Sunne: It is the moſt healthfull or well ayred land to live
<pb facs="tcp:17599:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> in, of any whatſoever, for it hath many high and great mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, faire and open fields, freſh and fierce running wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, both cleare and wholeſome, with innumerable ſprings and brookes mingled throughout the whole land.</p>
            <p>And that I may be the more brief in deſcribing thereof, if the native forme &amp; fertilitie of a whole Kingdome may bee underſtood by the like properties of a Province in another kingdome: then the kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> is moſt like to the County of <hi>Kent</hi> of any part in England, &amp; that in diverſe reſpects, for though they differ far in quantity; yet not verie much in quality, becauſe they aggree in theſe three.</p>
            <p>Some parts of the realme of <hi>Scotland</hi> doe yeeld great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, but litle pleaſure, ſafe only the pleaſure which doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company profite, and theſe be all the valleys or valey ground (for the moſt part through the whole kingdome): which (in diverſe reſpects) is eſteemed either to be better of it ſelfe, or els far better laboured, than any of whatſoever kingdome.</p>
            <p>Other parts againe doe yeeld great pleaſure but litle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and theſe bee, moſt of all the hills, banks, moores, and marriſhes: for ſome of theſe be moſt convenient for haulking, &amp; others for hunting, becauſe there be greateſt ſtore of wild fowle, and veniſon in theſe places,</p>
            <p>And ſome parts are mixed both with all the meanes, and kinds of profite and objects of pleaſure, and theſe bee, theſe which doe conſiſt partly of hill and partly of dale ground, and are ſituated betweene the ſides of all the rivers, ſprings, brooks or armes of the ſeas, and the tops of all the hills, or banks next adj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cent or adjoying thereunto.</p>
            <p>Theſe vertuous inhabitants of that worthy nation doe ſow and labour all the parts of the land that may be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſowne and laboured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and do yeeld ſufficiency of increaſe and leave all other parts for graſſe, hay, woods and parks, ſo that by the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g of GOD upon their labours, they have both plenty of bread and ſufficiency of milk and honey, when as people of other countries (which are both hotter &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yea and might be eaſier laboured, for want of labouring) have ſcarcitie.</p>
            <p>This commeth to paſſe moſt uſually in dry yeares (ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:17599:20"/> both the two laſt, &amp; agreat part of this) when the heat of the Sun burnes up even the beſt g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſe of their fatt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which if it had beene applyed to corne, the height or length of the ſtalk or ſtraw thereof would have better borne out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the drought: ſo that if theſe people doe not learne of laborious Scottiſhmen, and put their hands better to work, they ſhall have neither bread nor milk to eate, far leſſe fleſh for all their graſſe.</p>
            <p>But although <hi>I</hi> might inſiſt largly here not only in deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing that famous realme, and the due commendation of the worthie inhabitants thereof, and that for their excellent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, (the like wherof ſo many, or at leaſt in ſuch meaſure no nation hath) &amp; theſe be <hi>wiſdome, fidelity, magnanimity, learning induſtry, frugality liberality, ſtability, dexterity, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lerity, &amp; pati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence:</hi> but likwiſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l the other matchles prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ties of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient kingdom, which by divine providence do for the moſt part flow from thoſe, even as they doe from the fountaine of all goodneſſe: but leſt the illuſtration thereof ſhould bee too large I refer the Reader to that Treatiſe called, <hi>The rare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of Scotland,</hi> and doe only expreſſe them heere as I did the other: returne to our intended matter, and draw it to a concluſion. The prerogatives are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Scotland was never conquered. 2. It hath the greateſt ſucceſſion of Kings. 3. Scottiſhmen are the moſt excellent warriours. 4. Scotland is the beſt fortifier of other nations. 5. The Roman Emperours wall of defence from the Scotts. 6. Scottiſhmen are moſt compleetly bred and fattheſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled. 7. Scotland is an exact abridgment of the whole World. 8 Scotland can beſt ſerve it ſelf without traffick 9. Scotland hath the ſtrongeſt buildings, 10. and the rareſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, both naturall and artificiall of any cuntrie. 11. and to crowne all the reſt, Scotland made the moſt religious cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of any nation ſince the dayes of the goſpell in the happy reigne of King <hi>Iames</hi> of bleſſed memory.</p>
            <p>Thus the the whole premiſſes partly expreſſed and partly to be underſtood being well pondered and conſidered, is not the antient kingdome of Scotland juſtly eſteemed by many, and ought it not to bee generally accounted by all, the moſt renouned kingdome &amp; ſo his Majeſty the moſt famous King in all the World?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And will it not it follow by true conſequence that a Scot-ſman is ſo much the more able to proſecute whatſoever he underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and therefore ſo much the more to be reſpected by how much he is more ingenuous than one of another nation?</p>
            <p>And why then, is there any more prejudicate opinion taken by any of me in my profeſſion, but rather the poſſibility thereof more truſted, and the probability more expected, than if <hi>I</hi> were one of another nation?</p>
            <p>Now I with this litle bark being arrived at the haven unto which I intended, and after ſhe and <hi>I</hi> have both beene driven ſo far out of the way beyond all expectation at the firſt, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſo great dangers not only of ſtrong men of war: &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary winds, but have paſt through ſo many difficulties both of rocks &amp; quick ſands, <hi>I</hi> proceed where I left.</p>
            <p>Howſoever this task of teaching to write in ſix hours may ſeem either to be hard or impoſſible, becauſe it is rare or more than ordinary, yet it is effected by ordinary meanes through Gods aſſiſtance, unto whom all good things are poſſible, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be rare or frequent, and who giveth the ſucceſſe to every thing he ſeeth good, not withſtanding all &amp; whatſoever impediments which any way do croſſe his good purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And that it hath pleaſed him (who is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficient cauſe of all goodnes) firſt to grant me the knowledg, next the practiſe, &amp; thirdly the dexterity even to do good to others as well as my ſelf by both: and fourthly to aſſiſt me in that profeſſion hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, I prove at large in the firſt part of this work, or Art of Expedition, and that by the manifold effects both of what I (by his aſſiſtance) have formerly done, &amp; now profeſſe to do.</p>
            <p>Which if any do diſtruſt, or think ſtill imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſible (although very probable) I hope if they wil but believe their own eys e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by preſent ptactiſe, to give them ſuch content, as hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth they ſhall have no reaſon but to be ſilent.</p>
            <p>Although the time preſcribed be only ſix hours, yet I doe neither exclude longer time, aſwell for attaining further per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of degries and celerity or ſpeed, by much &amp; often pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe after, as due theorie, true way or perfection of parts both of skill &amp; ſpeed by dexterity or rationall knowledg thereof.</p>
            <p>Neither yet do I preſcribe ſo ſtrict or ſhort a time to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh this buſineſſe as a preciſe task to all alike, becauſe all are neither alike capable to learne, nor alike carefull to practiſe
<pb facs="tcp:17599:21"/> nor yet to practiſe alike carefully nor conſtantly what they learne, yea even although they be men of age, learning &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and have time &amp; opportunity.</p>
            <p>And although all that do learne of one teacher may be alike equally taught, yet all cannot be alike ſpeedily taught, becauſe all cannot alike ſpeedily learne; therefore ſome muſt have lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time than others, not in their teachers default, for hee can teach them as ſoone as others, but in their owne, who cannot learne ſo ſpeedily as others, yea and although they could, yet if they be either not ſo carefull to practiſe, or that they doe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe not ſo carefully and conſtantly as others, they will come ſo much ſhorter of their intent, and ſo will require ſo much longer time than others.</p>
            <p>Doe not both many of us ſee by dayly practiſe, and ſome of us feele by dolefull experience, that althogh painfull Preachers do never ſo equaly deliver Gods word to al their auditors, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey cannot teach them all alike ſpedily, becauſe they cannot all learne alike ſpeedily, neither though they could, are they all alike carefull to practiſe, and far leſſe to doe it alike carefully, &amp; conſtantly, &amp; ſo in theſe things ſtands all the difference.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is evident that although writing bee never ſo equally taught to many, &amp; well learned by ſome, yet it is only kept by thoſe who practiſe it, and that both carefully and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly: at leaſt halfe an houre in a day, till they have it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as there is great difference aſwell betweene tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and learners thereof as of other things, and ſometimes defects on each ſide for want either of skill or care, if not of both, ſo there is great difference alſo betwene le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ners throgh the ſame defects: as the Sun ſhining on diverſe objects ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth diverſity of effects.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <p>SInce the firſt ſheet heereof was printed, the Profeſſor hath removed to a countrie houſe in <hi>Kemmington,</hi> which adioyneth to <hi>Newington-butts,</hi> (alitle above the ſigne of Iacobs Well, about a mile from <hi>London,</hi> and halfe a mile from <hi>Westminſter)</hi> where hee uſually attendeth everie morning till ten a clock and the reſt of the day at the ſigne of the Spectacles over againſt the royall Exchange.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="penmanship_sample">
            <pb facs="tcp:17599:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
